<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

    <properties>
        <title>ICAT Release Notes</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="4.4.0">
            <p>This introduces a number of "RESTful" calls and has some other small improvements.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>A partial prototype of a "RESTful" interface has been added.</li>
                <li>There is a new parameter maxEntities which must be specified in icat.properties to restrict the total number of entities returned
                    in calls to get, search and searchText.
                </li>
                <li>There is a new parameter maxIdsInQuery which must be specified in icat.properties to restrict the size of ICAT generated queries.
                    This must not exceed 1000 if Oracle is being used.
                </li>
                <li>There are new parameters importCacheSize and exportCacheSize which must be specified in icat.properties to restrict the size of
                    caches used during import and export. The cache is local to a call to import or export to ensure that authorization rules are
                    enforced. As a by-product modifications to ICAT are less likely to result in stale information being returned from the cache.
                </li>
                <li>ID values are obtained from the database SEQUENCE table in groups of 500 rather than 50 to improve performance. This is to
                    circumvent a problem seen occasionally in Oracle.
                </li>
                <li>The DISTINCT keyword now works as in regular JPQL.</li>
                <li>Queries are now truncated to 4000 characters before storing them in the table or file log.</li>
                <li>The installation script has been made more robust and will also ensure that JDBC connectors are set up in a resilient manner for
                    Oracle RAC servers.
                </li>
                <li>It is now treated as an error to have redundant paths in an INCLUDE clause.</li>
                <li>The application is now built and deployed as a .war files rather than a .ear file which makes it easier to deploy on Wildfly.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.3.3">
            <p>This is a bug fix release with support for a group of ICATs working together. It is not a cluster in the Glassfish sense.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>The isAccessAllowed call, when used to check CREATE access, is now protected from invalid input.
                </li>
                <li>All standard JPQL functions are now accepted in search() calls.
                </li>
                <li>Queries returning results of aggregate functions should always return an array of length 1. However, due to the behaviour of JAXB
                    a list containing just a null is not transmitted properly and instead an empty list is returned. This is a problem with the
                    functions MIN, MAX, SUM and AVG all of which return null when they have no data to process. The COUNT function was also returning
                    an empty list when it had no data but now returns a list containing 0L.
                </li>
                <li>More than one ICAT may be used together to share the load and provide more resilience.
                </li>
                <li>The setup script does not require calling with the configure option.</li>
                <li>The icat-setup.properties file now uses the keyword dbProperties rather than icatProperties.</li>
                <li>Fixed bug with handling of unary minus.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.3.2">
            <p>This is a bug fix release.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>A get call using the old (non-JPQL) syntax will now accept the INCLUDE keyword in lower or mixed case.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.3.1">
            <p>This is a bug fix release.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>The methods logout and refresh when called with an expired or otherwise invalid sessionId now throw an exception of type SESSION
                    rather than INTERNAL.
                </li>
                <li>A small improvement to testicat has been made to show who you are logged in as.</li>
                <li>The relationship from DataCollection to DataCollectionParameters is now called parameters and can be accessed by getParameters and
                    setParameters.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.3.0">
            <p>This includes schema changes and a number of speculative features.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>The "ICATCompat" service for backwards compatibility with ICAT 3.x has now been removed.
                </li>
                <li>A method "void refresh(String sid)" has been added to refresh an ICAT session.
                </li>
                <li>The notification mechanism has been completely changed.</li>
                <li>It is not legal in queries with an INCLUDE to use a "1" in conjunction with and entity name. This will now reliably throw an
                    exception.
                </li>
                <li>A new call "boolean isAccessAllowed" has been created to test whether a specific access type is allowed.
                </li>
                <li>A call has been provided to return all the available entity names. This is of more use to tools than regular users.</li>
                <li>Column names in the Database table for UserGroup have been changed as they were inconsistent.</li>
                <li>The Rule entities are now store in a database table called RULE_. for compatibility with Microsoft SQLServer.</li>
                <li>A file indices.sql is being distributed with the .ear file with indices which may improve performance. You should assess whether
                    or not each index will be useful to your installation for while an index can give a huge improvement to a query there is also a
                    cost in maintaining an index.
                </li>
                <li>JPA mappings for floating point numbers now use precision 38 and scale 19. This is still not good on Oracle as mentioned in the
                    installation instructions.
                </li>
                <li>testicat.py (which replaces test.py) expects https://hostname:port rather than a pair of parameters</li>
                <li>Call logging has been added either to file or to a log table or both.</li>
                <li>Lucene free text search has been included via the new searchText call.</li>
                <li>
                    Changed uniqueness constraints to:
                    <dl>
                        <dt>Datafile</dt>
                        <dd>dataset, name (-location)</dd>
                        <dt>Dataset</dt>
                        <dd>investigation, name (-sample -type)</dd>
                        <dt>Application</dt>
                        <dd>facility, name, version (+facility)</dd>
                        <dt>Sample</dt>
                        <dd>investigation, name (-type)</dd>
                        <dt>Investigation</dt>
                        <dd>facility, name, visitid (-facilityCycle -instrument)</dd>
                        <dt>SampleType</dt>
                        <dd>facility, name, molecularFormula (+molecularFormula)</dd>
                    </dl>
                </li>
                <li>Made all constraint fields not nullable. This is checked by ICAT to ensure that future changes do not break this rule.</li>
                <li>Add a string attribute: "arguments" to the job to
                    store the program arguments that were used.
                </li>
                <li>Relationship between
                    FacilityCycle and Investigation removed.
                </li>
                <li>Table between Investigation and
                    Instrument added to represent many-to-many relationships between them.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Added DataCollection and changed Job to make use if it.
                </li>
                <li>Group has been changed to Grouping as Group is a JPQL keyword.</li>
                <li>Add attribute 'url' to Instrument.</li>
                <li>Added new alternate query syntax that may be used in queries and authz rules. It is distinguished by starting with the keyword
                    "SELECT".
                </li>
                <li>It is no longer considered an error to have no authz rules matching a search call - you just get no data back.</li>
                <li>Packaging now conforms to http://code.google.com/p/icatproject/wiki/ComponentGuidelines</li>
                <li>
                    A command
                    <tt>icatadmin</tt>
                    has been introduced to perform operations for which the rule based authorization is not appropriate.
                </li>
                <li>Expired sessions are cleaned out of the database every hour.</li>
                <li>The generated client jar contains two packages: org.icatproject and org.icatproject_4_3_0. Normal users should use the
                    org.icatproject one. The other exists primarily for TopCAT so that multiple ICAT clients can co-exist.
                </li>
                <li>The installation mechanism now has a single setup Python script which works both on Linux and Windows.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.2.5">
            <p>
                This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0, 4.2.1, 4.2.2, 4.2.3 or 4.2.4 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and
                deploy the new one. If you have changed log4j.properties from the one supplied then add an entry to your icat.properties:
                <tt>log4j.properties = log4j.properties</tt>
                which tells the ICAT to use the existing log4j.properties file in the config directory rather than the built in one. If you have not
                changed it then it is preferable to delete the log4j.properties from the config directory to avoid any possible confusion. The
                log4j.properties file is no longer reread, if you have configured your own copy and wish to change it then you must at least reload
                ICAT for the properties file to be read again.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    A significant leak has been fixed which was causing an unlimited number of threads to be created. This has been addressed by
                    changing the way in which the log4j.properties file is read. Only if you have a line in the icat.properties identifying a specific
                    log4j.properties file will that file be used, otherwise a default file packaged within the .ear file will be used.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>


        <section name="4.2.4">
            <p>This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0, 4.2.1, 4.2.2 or 4.2.3 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy
                the new one.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Version number updated to 4.2.4 and test updated to ensure that the version corresponds to the maven project version.
                </li>
                <li>LICENSE.txt file added to top directory of the source tree.
                </li>
                <li>Creating an Investigation which refers to a new InvestigationUser now works properly.</li>
                <li>Using INCLUDE with User and Group now works properly. Previously it could throw a null pointer exception.</li>
                <li>Database requirements have been made more precise in the deployment instructions.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.2.3">
            <p>This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0, 4.2.1 or 4.2.2 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new
                one.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Two different error conditions were not being handled correctly in calls to createMany when a user attempted to violate a
                    uniqueness constraint. In the case of a conflict with a pre-existing entry in ICAT the offset returned was -1. In the case that
                    there were duplicates in the list passed in the call to createMany - rather than conflicts with existing database entries - an
                    IcatException of type INTERNAL was being thrown, also with an offset of -1. These bugs are now fixed.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.2.2">
            <p>This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0 or 4.2.1 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new one.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>A bug causing read access to be denied in certain circumstances, when it should have been permitted, has been fixed.
                </li>
                <li>When attempting to format an error message about an invalid list of INCLUDES a null pointer exception is no longer thrown.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.2.1">
            <p>This is a bug fix release. If you already have 4.2.0 installed, then simply remove the old ear file and deploy the new one.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Authorization rules without explicit relationships to groups (of the form "Investigation &lt;-&gt; InvestigationUser &lt;-&gt;
                    User [name =
                    :user]") now work properly.
                </li>
                <li>It is now possible to use boolean values in queries. Attributes can be compared against literal values of TRUE and
                    FALSE (not case
                    sensitive) as in "ParameterType [enforced = TRUE]"
                </li>
                <li>Null pointer exceptions were being throw with some authorization rules when using an Oracle database. This has now been fixed.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.2.0">
            <p>This introduces a clean mechanism for handling authentication plugins and provides significant speed enhancements.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>ICAT now contains no authentication plugins but it does provide an Authenticator interface for plugin writers. If you plan to use
                    the new authn_db database authentication plugin you will need to manually move data from the old table to the new passwd table.
                </li>
                <li>The login call now accepts two parameters, the mnemonic for the authentication plugin and a map of credentials. This change
                    necessitated the increase in the version number to 4.2.
                </li>
                <li>There was a serious performance bug in release 4.1 and to a lesser extent in 4.0. In both case this affected read operations -
                    search and get. This bug in the marshalling of the XML has now been addressed.
                </li>
                <li>Previously JMS messages had the property "query" set to the primary key and the actual query value was not available. They are now
                    assigned correctly to the properties "query" and "entityId".
                </li>
                <li>You will need an up-to-date version of JAX-WS such as the one packaged with Glassfish 3.1.2</li>
                <li>The main database schema is almost unchanged. The only difference is that some text fields have been made larger. </li>
                <li>A bug has been fixed in the handling of enum types in expressions.</li>

            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="4.1.1">
            <p>This is a bug fix release.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Aggregate functions (MIN, MAX, AVG, COUNT etc) no longer generate an internal exception.</li>
                <li>Minor improvements to the installation documentation.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>


        <section name="4.1.0">

            <p>This is the first release of ICAT4 which is meant to be approaching production quality.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    More changes to the API - too numerous to list here providing
                    <ul>
                        <li> support for pluggable authn,</li>
                        <li> support for rule based authz,</li>
                        <li>support for notifications and</li>
                        <li> a powerful search mechanism</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Database independent</li>
                <li>More regular schema with simple provenance mechanism</li>
            </ul>

        </section>

        <section name="4.0">
            <p> Technology
                preview release - not for production use
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li> Many changes to the API</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section name="3.3.4">
            <ul>
                <li> Changed the JPA provider from TopLink to EclipseLink</li>
                <li>Removed Dataportal from the installation</li>
            </ul>

        </section>

        <section name="3.3.3">
            <p>Public release</p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
            
            
   